A Guide to the Atcheson L. Hench Autograph Collection
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Medieval and Early European Manuscripts
  - 1722/23 March 8 "His Majestys [King George] Royal Charter For Incorporating The Governor and Company of Chelsea Water Works," for the city of Westminster and the County of Middlesex, with an index at the beginning of the document, Contemporary Copy, 64 pages, on paper, bound on the side with a cord, Hench # 37 (6435-a) (oversize)
  - 1727 June 14 Note concerning the overflow of Earwell Pond, which usually portended an extraordinary event such as the death of a king or queen, referring to the death of George I, on paper (6435-a) (Box-folder 5:1)
  - ca. 1739 "Manners A Satire" by Paul Whitehead (1710-1774), in verse, on paper nine pages sewn together with thread, published in 1739, Hench # 46 (6435-a) (Box-folder 5:2)
  - 1741 October 25 William Anne Keppel, second Earl of Albemarle, Governor of Virginia (1737-1754) to an unidentified correspondent, promising to give orders to his servant to attend the correspondent's steward at Aldenham, a village in Watford, Hertfordshire, and to settle his account about the rent for the house, apologizing for his delay in taking care of the matter, 1 page, paper, Hench # 43 (6435-a) (Box-folder 5:3)
  - 1744 March 1 Commission, to Captain de Mitry, in the Lorraine Guards, signed by King Louis XV, vellum, Hench # 54 (6435-i) (oversize)
  - ca. 1750 "A Glossary of Old English Words, Taken out from Shakespeare's, Spencer's, and Milton's Works," ca. 200 pages, on paper, bound in calf, with title stamped on spine, Hench # 41 (6435-a) (Box-folder 5:4)
  - 1765, n.d. Commonplace Book with Accounts, 44 pages on paper, containing notes on British history, politics, [Jonathan] Swift, Biblical subjects, and religion, Lord Robert Manners (1758-1782), officer of the Royal Navy, is mentioned in the accounts section of the green cardboard bound volume, Phillipps Ms 20274, Hench # 38 (6435-a) (Box-folder 5:5)
  - 1780 Official copy of a marriage contract, May 1, 1679, between Claude de la Fond and Rose Francoise de Mougenot, on vellum with paper covers bound together with a ribbon, Hench # 55 (6435-i) (Box-folder 5:6)
  - 1790-1791 Letter book of Charles Buck (1771-1815) a Congregational minister and secretary to Hoxton Academy, born at Hillsley, near Wotton under Edge, Gloucestershire, 236 pages on paper, bound with cardboard and vellum, Hench # 44 (6435-a) (Box-folder 5:7)
  - ca. 1790 "Political Dialogue Between Mr. Fairdebate & Mr. Meanwell," a political dialogue on the propriety of petitioning the king to remove the Minister, without alleging proofs of his misconduct, 10 pages on paper, Hench # 47 (6435-a) (Box-folder 5:8)
  - 1794 Bound volume of songs, called "Catches, Glees of Serious Cast, and Glees," possibly copied from a printed work, 13 pages on paper with a paper cover, Hench # 48 (6435-a) (Box-folder 5:9)
  - [early?] 18th century Copies of Extracts of Letters from Algernon Sidney to his father, the Earl of Leicester, Robert Sidney, 1659-1660, written while abroad in exile during the restoration of the monarchy, from Copenhagen, Stockholm, Frankfurt, and Rome, 52 pages on paper, bound in a volume with "Sidney letters" stamped on the spine, Hench # 42 (6435-a) (Box-folder 5:10)
  - early 18th century Manuscript volume, gold-lettered on spine: "Recueil historique"; containing brief descriptions of France, the social and political systems, and a lengthy section, "Abregé de l'histoire de France"; said to be by Charles Couthier, 504 pages on paper, in French with indexes in the back and a fold-out genealogical chart for the Bourbon dynasty, bound in red morocco and gilt, Hench # 56 (6435-i) (Box-folder 6:1)
  - [early 18th century] "Memoirs of Sir John Langham, Baronet," who dominated the spice trade, gave large sums to charity, and was an ally of Charles II during the Restoration, on paper, bound with paper covers, Hench # 45 (6435-a) (Box-folder 6:2)
  - 18th century Extracts from The Paradoxal Discourses of F.M. Van Helmont concerning the Macrocosm and Microcosm, 14 pages on paper, in English and Latin, Hench # 35 (6435-a) (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Late 18th & 19th cen. Memoir of John Mason, written by himself in the form of several letters, mentions his marriage to his wife Anne on page 40, describes his origin in hardship and poverty and his rise through agricultural industry, 182 pages on paper, Hench # 51 (6435-a) (Box-folder 6:4)
  - 1811 September-1812 January Journal kept by Sir Charles Witham (1791-1853), a naval officer, ca. 100 pages on paper, contains a drawing of a barn and windmill, bound but with front cover detached; also present is a genealogical letter about the Witham family addressed to a Mr. William, Hench # 49 (6435-a) (Box-folder 6:5)
  - ca. 1826 Selection of Entries from Roger Wilbraham's An Attempt at a Glossary of Cheshire Words, Bound paper manuscript in blue paper cover, about ten pages used, Hench # 50 (6435-a) (Box-folder 6:6)
  - 19th century Handwritten Transcripts of early documents concerning the Manor of Northolt [also written Northall in the volume], in the Hundred of Elthorn, Middlesex, 1339-1724, made by R.J. Whitwell, ca. 110 pages of the volume used, on paper with a cloth binding, Hench # 52 (6435-a) (Box-folder 6:7)
  - 20th century Postcards with pictures of highly decorative initials from a [missal?], Sienna, Italy, 2 items (Box-folder 6:8)
- Series II: Collection of Modern Autographs
  - 1874 March 22 Charles Francis Adams (1807-1886), Boston, to W.W. Crannell, Albany, New York, thanking him for the clippings of editorial comments concerning himself which Crannell sent to Adams, 1 page (6435-az) (Box-folder 6:9)
  - 1887 June 22 Alexander Agassiz (1835-1910) to "Dear Sir," informing his correspondent that the Museum of Comparative Zoology, Cambridge, Massachusetts, does not have the funds to purchase new collections, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 6:10)
  - 1880 February 11 Mark Alexander (1792-1883), Mecklenburg County, Virginia, to T.J. Burton, describing his political service, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 6:11)
  - 1791 [March 17?] Christopher Anstey (1724-1805) to [John?] White, due to Mrs. White's illness, he writes asking if he can have White's children at his house with their nursery servant so she can rest, 1 page (6435-a) (Box-folder 6:12)
  - [1873?] January 14 Samuel Chapman Armstrong (1839-1893) to Dr. [Andrew Preston?] Peabody (1811-1893), asking Dr. Peabody to write an account of a sermon by the Reverend Mr. Mars, "a colored preacher" who he heard on Revere Street, Boston, for the paper The Southern Workman. He also sends a copies of the paper and his report to the Superintendent of Public Instruction, describes the growth in applications for the Hampton Institute, the push for funds for new buildings, and a new singing campaign in the United States and England featuring the old slave spirituals to raise money for new dormitories. He also mentions the devastation of the Great Boston Fire of 1872, 4 pages (6435) (Box-folder 6:13)
  - 1938 January 28 Nancy Astor (1879-1964) to the Secretary of Labor, Frances Perkins, (1882-1965) explaining that arrangements had been made to meet the Congressional women and that would prevent her from having tea with Perkins while in Washington, D.C., 1 page (6435-an) (Box-folder 6:14)
  - 1859 April 25 The Reverend Thomas Atkinson (1807-1881) to the Reverend John Sinclair, [England?], sends a letter of introduction for University of Virginia Professor, James P. Holcombe, who is traveling in Europe for his health, 1 page (6435-y) (Box-folder 6:15)
  - 1893 March 5 Henry Bacon, American architect, (1866-1924) to his cousin, discussing his article "The Republic's First Statue" and drawing (neither present) about the work of Jean-Antoine Houdon for publication in his cousin's magazine, 4 pages on 2 l. (6435-ah) (Box-folder 6:16)
  - 1874 September 10 Philip James Bailey (1816-1902) to the Rev. J[ohn] G[eorge] Wood (1827-1889), while visiting Jersey Island, Bailey was reminded of his friend, the Rev. Wood, by meeting an acquaintance of Wood's named Mr. Blount of Belvedere, and by a letter that he forwards to Wood for an answer. He also enclosed some of his own work and some of an ancestor's work as well (not present), 4 pages, on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 6:17)
  - [1837] June 30 Joanna Baillie, Scottish poetess (1762-1851) to Mary Russell Mitford (1787-1855), informing her that "since the age of annuals began (a good many years now) I have always refused to contribute to them, though many of their most eminent editors requested me to do so and to make my own terms, because I did not like that species of literature. This may be prejudice in me, but I am certainly as averse to it now as I ever was…" She does wish Mitford the greatest success with her new undertaking and also mentions Lady [Barbarina Brand] Dacre (1768-1854), her daughter, Arabella Sullivan (1796-1839), Lady Beecher (formerly Miss O'Neil), Mr. Harness, and Sir Walter Scott in her letter., 5 pages, (6435-a) (Box-folder 6:18)
  - 1878 March 20 George Bancroft (1800-1891) to Charles Henry Hart (1847-1918), he is looking forward to reading the life of [Robert] Morris and expresses his appreciation for the letter from Langdon and the engravings sent by Hart, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-av) (Box-folder 6:19)
  - [n.y.] April 30 George Bancroft (1800-1891) to Aaron Hobart, Boston Reading in its entirety, "Your favor of the 18th is before me; and is already attended to in both its particulars.", 1 page, (6435-aq) (Box-folder 6:20)
  - 1829 January 5 James Barbour (1775-1842) to Thomas Aspinwall, Consul General of the United States, repays him for the advance payment he has made to the account of destitute seaman by encloses a draft on the Bankers of the United States, 1 page on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 7:1)
  - 1829 March 28 James Barbour (1775-1842) to Thomas Aspinwall, Consul General of the United States, in reply to his request, he encloses a draft on the Bankers of the United States for two hundred pounds, 1 page on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 7:1)
  - 1841 January 26 James Barbour (1775-1842) to Thomas Aspinwall, Consul General of the United States, asks for his help with a question currently in Federal court, "what was the southern boundary of the Cherokee Indians on the Tennessee or Cherokee River and the Mississippi in and before 1779?" Barbour suspects that this information may reside in the Colonial Office in London or in the reports of the Commissioners or Agents of Indian Affairs. He tells Aspinwall to send any authenticated information or maps concerning the matter to William Kinney, Staunton, Virginia, in the care of Read and Taylor, Maiden Lane, New York., 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 7:2)
  - 1827 August James Barbour (1775-1842) concerning the case of H. D[umas] and his claim for payment to Barbour as Secretary of War, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 7:3)
  - 1827 January 29 James Barbour (1775-1842) to George Graham, requests to borrow $6,000 dollars from the local branch of the Bank of the United States because of his heavy crop losses of the year before, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 7:4)
  - 1821 July 25 James Barbour (1775-1842) to "Dear Sir," inquires about his success in converting the one hundred and fifty dollars of bank notes left with him in the winter into something valuable and suggests Mr. Barclay of the Eastern Shore as an advisor if he needs one, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 7:5)
  - 1840 August 6 James Barbour (1775-1842) to "Gentlemen" [Whigs of Massachusetts], though much flattered by their invitation to attend a General Convention on Bunker Hill with the Whigs of Massachusetts in September, Barbour feels unable to endure the fatigue of such a journey but states "Massachusetts and Virginia - shoulder to shoulder - achieved the liberties of America; now that they are again in danger - may we by alike united and glorious effort maintain them,", 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 7:6)
  - 1822-1830 Philip Pendleton Barbour (1783-1841) - Financial documents, 3 bank drafts drawn upon the Branch Bank of the United States Bank at Washington (6435) (Box-folder 7:7)
  - 1812 Joel Barlow (1754-1812), document stating that Barlow was U.S. plenipotentiary to France with a ink stamp of the American Legation seal affixed (6435) (Box-folder 7:8)
  - 1908 February 19 Clara Barton (1821-1912) to her nephew, Sam, hand-written copy, sending her regret that he was so ill, 2 pages on 1 l. Note by Hench says the original was given to his mother for her collection as a birthday present on January 29, 1942 (6435) (Box-folder 7:9)
  - 1861 March 28 Kate Josephine Bateman (1842-1917), American actress, provides a brief note and autograph (6435) (Box-folder 7:10)
  - 1782 November 3 James Beattie (1735-1803) Scottish poet and abolitionist, to the Reverend Dr. James, thanking him for his son's poem, which he favorably analyzes, and mentioning the literary work of his own son, 2 p. on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 7:11)
  - 183[?] August 31 Sir Charles Bell (1774-1842), Scottish physician and anatomist, to Sir John Richardson (1787-1865), physician and Arctic explorer, hand-written copy, sharing experiences of his trip through England, focusing chiefly upon fishing. Note by Hench says the original was given to his brother, Philip Hench, for his medical autograph collection as a birthday present on February 18, 1941 (6435-a) (Box-folder 7:12)
  - [1855] October 29 Park Benjamin, Sr. (1809-1864) to the Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Sciences, asking if they can arrange for a speaking date after December 27th since he may not return from his trip out West until December 20th, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 7:13)
  - 1862 April 2 Cyrus Billartin, publisher of the Newburgh Journal to Colonel [Charles Henry?] Van Wyck (1824-1895), colonel of the Fifty-sixth Regiment, New York Volunteers, asking him to send his weekly letters to his publication instead of the Press, so they will not be published a week behind his competitor due to the schedule of publication, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 7:14)
  - 1866 August 12 George Henry Boker (1823-1990) to Paul Hamilton Hayne, apologizes for having mislaid Hayne's note with his address; asks which of his sonnets is being used by [S. Adams] Lee in his "Book of the Sonnet" at Robert Brothers of Boston, because Boker is supposed to write a paragraph about Hayne and his poetry appearing in the book; expresses astonishment that [Richard Henry?] Stoddard did not reply to Hayne's note; and sends him a copy of his own Poems of the War and notes that one of his poems, "Countess Laura" was published in the Atlantic Monthly for August 1865, 4 pages on 1 l., with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 7:15)
  - 1841 October 14 Joseph Bosworth (1789-1876), Anglo-Saxon scholar and lexicographer to W[illiam] Jerdan (1782-1869), manager of the Literary Gazette, promises to promote its circulation, forwards some poems by Mr. Mark, Whisperings of Fancy, and encloses an order for a copy of what was published with his Anglo-Saxon dictionary, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 7:16)
  - 1883 August Poem "Books for the People" by Anne Charlotte Lynch Botta (1815-1891), 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 7:17)
  - n.d. Poem "To the Hon. Daniel Webster" by Anne Charlotte Lynch Botta (1815-1891), 4 pages, on 2 l. (6435) (Box-folder 7:17)
  - 1838 August 31 John Minor Botts (1802-1869) to William Ogden Niles, Editor of The Register, urges him to re-examine his books to find the payment he made last May and settle the claims of non-payment made by Philip Tabb or to question his own brother who took his payment, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 7:18)
  - 1840 September 15 John Minor Botts (1802-1869) to "My dear Sir," thanks his correspondent for giving him the news that he picks up during his travels which may prove advantageous to their cause, has had his first published and will provide extracts to [John Hampden ?] Pleasants, editor of the Richmond Whig from his last correspondence; he plans on go on a speaking campaign to address the people, saying "Was ever a party so whip't as we shall whip this truly Federal loco foco party"; and he also has received a letter from Lewis Williams of North Carolina predicting that [William Henry] Harrison will get a 15,000 majority of that state., 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 7:19)
  - 1926 Autograph of G[amaliel] Bradford in return address portion of an envelope (6435) (Box-folder 7:20)
  - 1789 August 10 John Breckenridge, Albemarle County, Virginia, to "Sir," offering himself to fill the position of clerk of the General Assembly recently vacated by J. Beckley, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 7:21)
  - 1865 April 1 John Bright (1811-1889) to Thomas Dixon, informs him that he cannot do anything more towards his object due to the press of letters and applications sent to him and asks him not to bother [Richard] Cobden either as he is ill; he also refers to the Civil War, "You will be glad, as I am, at the prospect of a termination of the great contest in America,", 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 7:22)
  - 1869 April 22 John Bright (1811-1889) to Sir John Jaffray (1818-1901), Scottish journalist and co-founder of the Birmingham Daily Post, writes that the successor of General [Cartwright] has been appointed; a copy of the Report of the Commission has been sent to Jaffray; and that he believes Jaffray will approve of the bill of [George Joachim?] Coschen (1831-1907) when he sees the amendments that he is ready to propose, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 7:23)
  - 1864 August 19 John Bright (1811-1889) to Dr. J[ohn] P[almer] Litchfield (1808-1868), Kingston, Cananda West, one of the founding faculty of The University of Queens College, School of Medicine, and former superintendent of the Asylum for the Criminally Insane at Rockwood in Kingston, about possible appointments for him, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 7:24)
  - 1851 March 18 John Bright (1811-1889) to J. Milne, informs him that the resolution of Mr. Bailles has been withdrawn but the conduct of those implicated in the "Ceylon business" [the crushing of the Matale Rebellion against taxes on the peasant class] was so bad that it would have been difficult to have argued or voted against his motion; Bright hesitates to show full support for the government, fearing that "we should soon lose our own characters, & at the same time fail to save the Whigs." Apparently, the letter was referring to the atrocities committed in Ceylon by the British under the administration of Lord Torrington., 3 pages on 1 l. (6435-aq) (Box-folder 7:25)
  - 1869 April 27 John Bright (1811-1889) to John Reed, sharing that "our government has cautioned the Governors of the Colonies not to encourage colonization in the Fiji Islands by holding out hope of British Protection; we cannot interfere in what the French or the Americans are doing there.", 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 7:26)
  - 1853 November 5 John Bright (1811-1889) John Bright to F.L. Scott, forwarding a letter from [William] Farley, a letter carrier for the Skinner Street District, to the Post Master General, Lord Charles John Canning (1812-1862); Farley is seeking an appointment for his son, Edward Farley, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435-an) (Box-folder 7:27)
  - 1873 December 8 John Bright (1811-1889) to Dr. Henry Thomas (1832-1894), homeopath of the Llandudno Hydropathic Establishment, encloses a note for Mr. Fowler thanking him for the picture, 1 page (6435-a) (Box-folder 7:28)
  - 1853 June 21 John Bright Autograph on a Pass to "Admit the Bearer to the Gallery" [of the House of Commons?] (6435-a) (Box-folder 7:29)
  - 1863 May 4 John Bright Autograph on a Pass to "Admit the Bearer to the Gallery of the House of Commons" (6435-av) (Box-folder 7:30)
  - 1790 January 9 Signature of G. Brooke, Clerk of Court, Dumfries, Virginia, on a legal document, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 7:31)
  - 1863 November 16 Lt. Colonel William LeRoy Broun (1827-1902), Confederate States Arsenal, to Major Thomas M. Bowyer, Dublin Depot, transferring the horse shoe contracts, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 7:32)
  - 1868 September 12 Max Bruch (1838-1920) to "Dear Friend," in German, with an English hand-written transcript, asking if they are going to play his concerto at one of the concerts in the Cloth-workers Hall and for a recommendation for a nice boarding house for his sister and himself in Leipzig, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 7:33)
  - 1885 September 17 Max Bruch (1838-1920) to "Dear Friend," in German, 4 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 7:34)
  - 1897 June 2 James Bryce (1838-1922) to Bishop [Henry Codman] Potter, Bishop of New York, hopes to visit with him while he is in London for a quiet talk about various American questions perplexing him, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435-ba) (Box-folder 7:35)
  - [1921?] June 20 James Bryce (1838-1922) to Mr. Quinn, tries to arrange a time when they could meet before he sails for America, 1 page (6435-ba) (Box-folder 7:36)
  - n.d. James Bryce (1838-1922) engraving, (6435-ba) (Box-folder 7:37)
  - 1834 May 3 Peter Buchan (1790-1854) to Messrs. Archibald Fullarton & Co. Publishers, Glasgow, discusses the publication of their edition of Burns' works with approval, especially the notes by M. presumably, William Motherwell (1797-1835), Editor of the Glasgow Courier, and the edition of Burns by Allan Cunningham, which contained "several gross mistakes, willful misrepresentations, or ignorant errors, particularly in the Songs." He offers his services in any manner to benefit their edition of Burns. Buchan also sends an old prospectus for a work not published due to a misunderstanding with Henry Constable, even though his manuscript had been read by Sir Walter Scott and others with approval, which he offers for publication., 3 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 7:38)
  - 1885 Hezekiah Butterworth (1839-1905), editor of Youth's Companion to Mr. Ernst, sends him scraps of verse for The Beacon, 4 pages on 4 l. (6435) (Box-folder 7:39)
  - n.d. Hezekiah Butterworth (1839-1905), editor of Youth's Companion to Miss Clara T. Scott, writes "It seems to me that Mr. [William Dean ?] Howells is the American Balzac, and that the true purpose of the novel is to so analyze life as make life better, more noble and happy.", 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 7:40)
  - 1964 June 19 Senator Harry F. Byrd, Sr. (1887-1966) to Atcheson L. Hench (1891-1974), expresses his deep appreciation of the Appalachian Trail and his intention to support the bill introduced by Senator Nelson, 1 page, typescript, with envelope (6435-at) (Box-folder 7:41)
  - 1892 December 25 William Lewis Cabell (1827-1911), Trans-Mississippi Department United Confederate Veterans, Dallas, Texas, to A.E. Allen, supplies the requested addresses of various generals, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 7:42)
  - [n.y.] November 22 Janet [Hamilton?] Carter, (wife of John Carter, 1739?-1789), Sudley Farm, [Prince William County?], Virginia, to John Fitzgerald, orders six yards of cloth in a note (6435) (Box-folder 7:43)
  - 1941 January 13 Hunsdon Cary (1872-1952) to Atcheson Hench (1891-1974), encloses a printed copy of his "Education Plank" pamphlet as a candidate for Virginia governor (6435) (Box-folder 7:44)
  - 1940 May 16 Willa Cather (1873-1947) to Atcheson Hench, with other related letters to publishers concerning a cheap edition of Death Comes for the Archbishop, in 1938 and 1949; Willa Cather discusses why she will not allow a contract renewal to print a Modern Library edition of her book for "poor students," 2 pages on 2 l. with envelope, copy, original in Vault- Cather (6435) (Box-folder 7:45)